<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tythes no maintenance for gospel-ministers, or, A seasonable discourse concerning tythes wherein it is fully proved that those that urge the payment thereof for their maintenance are no true gospel ministers, but antichristian, and do concur with priests of the Leviticall order and institution ... / by T.H. and T.R.</title>
            <author>Heath, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43226</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1344</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32342</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12638676</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12638676</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64968</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43226)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64968)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1528:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tythes no maintenance for gospel-ministers, or, A seasonable discourse concerning tythes wherein it is fully proved that those that urge the payment thereof for their maintenance are no true gospel ministers, but antichristian, and do concur with priests of the Leviticall order and institution ... / by T.H. and T.R.</title>
                  <author>Heath, Thomas.</author>
                  <author>Rosewell, Thomas, 1630-1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.A. for William Larner ... and Thomas Heath ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Heath.</note>
                  <note>"To all who love the Lord Iesus Christ in sincerity" signed: Thomas Heath, Thomas Rosewell.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Tithes --  England.</term>
               <term>Church and state.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64968:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Tythes no Maintenance FOR Goſpel-Miniſters: OR, A ſeaſonable Diſcourſe concerning Tythes.</p>
            <p>Wherein it is fully proved, That thoſe who urge the payment thereof for their mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, are no true Goſpel-Miniſters, but Antichriſtian, and do concur with Prietſts of the Leviticall Order and Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>Occaſioned by a PROPOSITION, with nine Reaſons laid down for the proof thereof, which was lately printed and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, holding forth the dreadfull danger of <hi>Sacriledge</hi> and ſin even in the higheſt nature in the with-holding of Tythes.</p>
            <p>Which ſaid PROPOSITION, with the Reaſons therein contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at large are hereunto annexed, the groſſe abſurdities thereof briefly diſcuſſed and confuted, and the Truth vindicated and cleered from thoſe miſts and foggs of Judaiſm and Antichriſtian darkneſſe which the <hi>Propoſer</hi> bath darkened it withall.</p>
            <p>By <hi>T. H.</hi> and <hi>T. R.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 John 4.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Beloved, believe not every ſpirit, but trie the ſpirits whether they are of God, becauſe many falſe Prophets are gone out into the world.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 2.9.—</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I know the blasphemy of them which ſay they are Jews and are not, but are the ſynagogue of Satan.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 6.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>For from the leaſt of them even to the greateſt of them, every one is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to covetouſneſſe, and from the Prophet even unto the Prieſt every one dealeth falſly.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. A.</hi> for <hi>William Larnar</hi> at the Black-Moore neer Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, and <hi>Thomas Heath</hi> in <hi>Martins is Grand.</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:64968:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64968:2"/>
            <head>To all who love the Lord Ieſus Chriſt in ſincerity.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the myſtery of iniquity did Login to work in the Apoſtles time? <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.7 2. Cor. 11.13, 14, 15.</note> if there were falſe Apoſtles, deceitfull work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, transforming themſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt? If there were the Miniſters of Satan? who were tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed as the Miniſters of righteouſneſſe, whoſe end ſhould be according to their works? And if we are exhorted to try the Spirits whether they are of God, <note place="margin">1 Joh. 4.1.</note> (upon this accompt) becauſe many falſe Prophets are gone out into the world. Then no marvell is it, that the factors and agents for Antichriſt are ſo encreaſed, and the Myſtery of Iniquity grown to ſuch maturity and ripeneſſe; nay (may we not rather ſay) to ſuch boldneſſe and impudency, that they are not aſhamed to open their pack of Romiſh Trumpery (we meane) their unwritten Traditions and humane Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the ſight and view of the whole world, and theſe their muſty and putrified wares, for ſound and ſubſtantiall commodities, would they force upon tender conſciences, whom God hath inlightned to
<pb facs="tcp:64968:3"/>diſcover the ſlights and cunning craftineſſe of theſe grand Impoſtors, <note place="margin">Eph. 4.14.</note> whereby they lye in wait to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive. One piece of which their Merchantable ſtuffe moſt cunningly and artificially woven together, with Scriptures abſurdly applied, and others as lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly perverted, is here preſented unto your view, whoſe eyes the Lord hath annoynted with his eye-ſalve to diſcern the wiles and workings of Satan in theſe men. <note place="margin">Rev. 3.18.</note> And although evill men and ſeducers ſhall wax worſe and worſe, <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.13.</note> deceiving, and being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, yet the righteous ſhall hold on his way, and he that hath clean hands ſhall be ſtronger and ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: <note place="margin">Job. 17.9</note> And although many deceivers are entred into the world, <note place="margin">2 John 7.</note> who confeſſe not that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, (and ſuch are all they, who would bring us back again unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> and preſſe the Obſervation of Leviticall Rites and Ceremonies upon the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which are altogether aboliſhed and done away by the coming of Jeſus Chriſt in the fleſh) And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Antichriſt by his Sorceries hath deceived the Nations, <note place="margin">Rev. 8.22. &amp; 19.20. Eſa. 44.20</note> and a deceived heart hath turned many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, that they cannot deliver their ſoul, nor ſay, Is <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ot a lye in my right hand? yet it is not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e, <note place="margin">Mat. 24.<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> that the Elect ſhall be deceived by them. Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved you are thoſe who are taught of God, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 54.13.1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.21. thoſe to whom he hath revealed his ſecrets, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.14. who have the gift of trying and diſcerning the Spirits, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.1. and therefore we could not but recommend unto you this enſuing Treatiſe, wherein we hope we have diſcovered the groſſe abſurdity of that Propoſition, and have vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated the truth from that error and darkneſſe which
<pb facs="tcp:64968:3"/>the Propoſer hath clouded it withall; and truly our conſciences do beare us witneſſe, that it was not out of any prejudice to the perſon of the Propoſer, but the love which we beare unto Truth, that did ſtir up our ſpirits to this undertaking; and the rather, ſo that the Author of the ſaid paper, who being a chief man of the Presbyterian Sect, and pretends himſelf a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Goſpell, hath ſaid ſuch high accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt the moſt conſcientious people, charging them with ſin in the higheſt aggravations thereof, with temporall and ſpirituall judgements accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying it, threatning alſo no leſſe then eternall death againſt them in a caſe where no Law is tranſgreſſed. And to inforce his accuſation and charge of ſin and judgement, how notoriouſly hath he wreſted and perverted the Scriptures? diſhonoring the Lord, and falſifying his truth, which was ſo great a trouble un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſpirits, that we could not be ſilent. Nor would we be thought to be diſobedient to that authority which God hath ſet over us, and under which we live, and through his bleſſing do enjoy much free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, protection, and preſervation.</p>
            <p>We profeſſe our ſubj<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction to Magiſtracy in all law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things that are commanded by them, only in the matters of God, and of his Chriſt our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and wherin the glory of God is ſo highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, it is our deſire to keep our conſciences pure and undefiled, remembring alwayes, that the Laws of God muſt have the preheminence, and all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Lawes and Ordinances muſt and ought to be ſubordinate thereunto. And in reference unto his Houſe, which is ſpirituall, we can acknowledge no
<pb facs="tcp:64968:4"/>other King or Law-giver ſave Chriſt alone: We look not to receive honour from men, <note place="margin">Joh. 5 44.</note> but we ſeek the honour that cometh from God onely. And if the Lord will vouchſafe to honour his Truth by ſuch poor and unworthy Inſtruments as we are, we ſhall account it honour enough.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Heath.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Roſewell.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:64968:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The dreadfull danger of</hi> Sacriledge, <hi>held forth in this one Propoſition: Namely,</hi> The with-holding of Tythes from a Miniſter that labours in the Word and Doctrine, or denying thoſe accuſtomed rates upon houſes, which have been paid to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſucceſsively, time out of mind, is a great and grievous ſin, highly diſpleaſing to Almighty God, as appears by theſe Reaſons.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> BEcauſe it is a direct breach of the eighth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, which ſaith, <hi>That thou ſhalt not ſteal;</hi> and directly contrary to the Rule of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Render therefore to all their dues, Cuſtome to whom Custome, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea Tythes are due to the Miniſter by the Law of the Land, and the Miniſter hath as legall a right to the rates ſet upon houſes, as the Landlord hath to his rent; therefore to deprive the Miniſter of them is a breach, not only of Gods Law, but alſo of mans Law, and <hi>who ſo breaketh this hedge; a Serpent ſhall bite him,</hi> Eccleſ. 10.8.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Object. <hi>But tythes are antichriſtian, and therefore not to be paid any longer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is a falſe opinion, as appears by this Argument; That which our Saviour enjoyned is not Antichriſtian, but our Saviour enjoyned tythes, Luke 11.42. <hi>Ye tythe, mint, and rue, and all manner of herbs, and paſſe over Judgement and the Love of God: theſe ought ye to have done;</hi> that is, ye ought to pay tythes, therefore they are not antichriſtian.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Object. <hi>But we do not come to hear him, why then ſhould we pay him, ſince we have no benefit by his Miniſtery?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64968:5"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If thou live in a Pariſh where a godly Miniſter is ſeated, thou art bound to hear him, for he worketh <hi>the work of the Lord, as well as theſe of greater parts.</hi> See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.10. If thou do not hear him, nor pay him, thou addeſt ſin to ſin; for firſt it is a ſin to withdraw thy preſence, and then it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, yea a greater ſin, to withdraw his maintenance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Object. <hi>But the Miniſter will not give us our due in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, therefore we may justly deny him his due?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, The Sacrament is not due to all, but onely to thoſe that come in a regular way, according to the order of the Goſpel, for all things muſt be done decently, and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.40. Now the order of the Goſpel is this, that the power of examining thoſe that are admitted to the Lords Supper, belongs not to the Miniſter alone, nor to the Miniſter with the whole Congregation, but to the Miniſter and ruling Elders, as is undeniably proved by that ſingular Treatiſe ſet forth by the Provincial Aſſembly, called <hi>the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Presbyterian Government, pag.</hi> 70, 71. Secondly, the Sacrament is not due to thoſe that live in any ſcandalous ſin; but theft, or robbing of God is a ſcandalous ſin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> It is a ſin of a high nature, becauſe it affronts God himſelf, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Will a man rob God? Yet ye have robbed me. But ye ſay, wherein have we robbed thee? in Tythes and Offerings.</hi> To rob a man by the high-way doth deſerve death, to rob a King of his Plate and Jewels deſerves a tormenting death, but to rob the King of Glory, deſerves the fire of hell.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> It is a complicated ſin, wherein fraud or cheating is added to theft: For the Landlord lets his houſe to the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant at a lower rate, upon this account; namely, that he ſhall pay the duties to the Miniſter: As for example, if the houſe be worth 21. l. <hi>per annum,</hi> the Landlord lets it for 20. l <hi>per annum,</hi> on purpoſe that the Tenant may (perhaps) pay twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhillings a year to the Miniſter. The Tenant notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing payes nothing, but keeps it back from the Miniſter by fraud, and puts the Landlords money in his pocket. Here is fraud with a Witneſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> It is a ſin, whereby godly Miniſters are diſcouraged
<pb facs="tcp:64968:5"/>in their work, their hands weakned, and their ſpirits bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ſo that they cannot go on in their Miniſtery with <hi>joy, but with griefe;</hi> this is directly contrary to the practiſe of that godly King <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> (whoſe example is written for our learning, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4.) for it is teſtified of him, 2 Chron. 31.4. <hi>that he commanded the people that dwelt in Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, to give the portion of the Priests and Levites, that they might be incouraged in the Law of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> It is a ſin wherein and whereby the defrauder robs his own ſoul of that ſpiritual benefit and advantage which he might get by ſuch a mans Miniſtery; for it is juſt with God to ſay to ſuch a man, thou withdraweſt maintenance from my ſervant, and I will withdraw my bleſſing from my own Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, ſo that the word preached (by whomſoever it be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed) ſhall do thee no good at all, but rather it ſhall be a ſavour of death, to thy own condemnation. Thy ſoule ſhall never thrive or proſper by any Sermon that thou heareſt.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> It is a ſin that provokes God to curſe a man in his outward eſtate and trading, as appears by that forenamed place, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Ye are curſed with a curſe, for ye have robbed me:</hi> It is uſuall with God to pay ſinners with their own coyn; they rob God in tythes, and God robs them of their trade and livelyhood; they grudge the Miniſters a maintenance, and God grudgeth them even bread for their Families, ſo that they uſually turn bankerupts, or are ſo much in debt, that they are aſhamed to ſhew their faces.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> It is a ſin againſt the Goſpel, becauſe it hinders the progreſs and ſucceſs of it, for ſuch men do as much as in them lies to extinguiſh the light, by taking away the oyl that feeds it. It is obſerved in that excellent bo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k <hi>Vindic. Presb Gov pag.</hi> 81. that <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, that curſed enemy of Chriſt and his Goſpell, did by taking away tythes do more miſchiefe to the Church of God, than all the perſecuting Emperors that were before him; for the Perſecutors took away only the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, (and their blond was the ſeed of the Church) but ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away tythes, took away the Miniſtery it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> It is a ſin will not be pardoned upon repentance, unleſſe there be a reſtitution as well as repentance, according
<pb facs="tcp:64968:6"/>to that of <hi>Anguſtine, Non remittitur peccatum, niſi reſtituatur ablatum,</hi> Thy ſin ſhall not be pardoned, unleſſe that which thou with-holdeſt unjuſtly be reſtored.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> It is a ſin that will cry for vengeance, when the ſinner on his death-bed is crying for mercy, as appears by that remarkable Scripture, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.2, 4. <hi>Your gold and ſilver is can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kered, and the ruſt of them ſhall be a witneſſe againſt, and ſhall eat your fleſh as it were with fire; Ye have heaped treaſure</hi> (that's of wrath) <hi>together for the laſt dayes. Behold the hire of the Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers which have reaped down your fields which is of you kept back by fraud crieth; and the cries of them which have reaped are entered into the ears of the Lord of Sabbath.</hi> Now if the hire of the Labourers in mens Vineyard, kept back by fraud crieth, how dreadfull will the cry be of the hire of Gods Labourers in Gods Vineyard, kept back by robbers and defrauders? I tremble to think of it.</p>
            <p>Conſider what hath been preſented unto you in this paper, and the Lord give ye underſtanding in all things.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis enſuing diſcourſe was intended for publike view before this time, but received ſome interruption, which occaſioned the delay thereof; yet we hope it will be <hi>ſeaſonable,</hi> and not prove <hi>Abortive,</hi> as one that it born out of due time: And though ſome have gone before us, whoſe ſpirits have been ſtirred up to the ſame undertaking, (for which we rejoyce and bleſſe God) yet we can truly ſay, we have not lighted our Candle at their Lamp: And in this we are very much comforted and incouraged, conſidering, that in the mouth of two or three Witneſſes, the Truth will receive the greater eſtabliſhment.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64968:6"/>
            <head>TYTHES No Maintenance for Goſpel-Miniſters: OR, A ſeaſonable Diſcourſe concerning TITHES, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E ſhall omit to inſert any thing as touching the name of the Author of the ſaid Propoſition, by reaſon that he is either afraid to own it, or aſhamed to publiſh it, remembring what our Saviour ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 3.20, 21. That <hi>every one that doth evill hateth the light, neither cometh to the light, leſt his deeds ſhould be reproved: but he that doth truth, cometh to the light, that his deeds may be made manifeſt, that they are wrought in God.</hi> But to the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ropoſition it ſelf.</p>
            <p>P. <hi>The witholding of tythes from a Miniſter that labors in the word and doctrine, or denying thoſe accustomed rates upon houſes which have been paid to Miniſters ſucceſſively time out of mind, is a great and grievous ſin, highly diſpleaſing to almighty God,</hi> as the Author or Publiſher of the ſaid Paper would make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64968:7"/>by the Reaſons laid down in the ſaid Paper.</p>
            <p>The Propoſition holds forth ſin diſpleaſing to God, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſhal reply ſomwhat as touching it, &amp; the grounds laid down to plead the force of his Propoſition, which are two. Firſt, <note place="margin">Here he ſheweth the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his argument, having no Scripture, but anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, which was from a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, which are not rules for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to obſerve.</note> his being a Miniſter that labors in the Word &amp; Doctrine; and ſecondly, <hi>accuſtomed rates ſet upon houſes, which have been paid ſucceſſively to ſuch Miniſters time out of mind.</hi> Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt, it would be very requiſite, that he would prove himſelf a true Miniſter ſet apart by God for that work, and choſen by a true Church which hath approved of his gifts; and then ſecondly, for cuſtome, we do affirm that they are not to be obeyed without they are grounded upon a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from God, or example out of the Word of God. But grant he were a true Goſpel-Miniſter, yet ought he not to plead cuſtome or antiquity, to force men to pay Tythes, which were due only to the Prieſts that ſerved at the Altar, <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.24, 26. under the Ceremoniall Leviticall Law: And as all types and ceremonies pointed to their anti-types, ſo the antitype being produced, the type ceaſeth: But Tythes were a ceremony of the Leviticall Law, and <hi>Chriſt is the end of the Law for righteouſneſſe to every one that believeth;</hi> and we hope, that none of them that call themſelves Goſpel-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, will be called Prieſts of the Leviticall Law, and preſſe Tythes for their maintenance, or rather as their wages, which was the wages of the Prieſts, <hi>Num.</hi> 18.31. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.12. which offered up ſacrifices and burnt-offerings; but Chriſt hath put an end to all Prieſthood and ſacrifice under the Law, and the Prieſthood being changed, there is made of neceſſity a change alſo of the Law, except you will ſhew us a command or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept under the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, ſhall not your perſon be maintained? We anſwer, if one that truly labours in the Word and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, would lay down a precept for his maintenance, let him ſhew what the Lord hath ordained; that <hi>they which preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.14.</note> but Tythes are not Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-precepts.</p>
            <p>Again, whereas you ſay, it is a ſin of that nature, as to term it <hi>ſacriledge,</hi> or robbing of God, we hope, you will be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64968:7"/>more calm in the cenſure of men, who through tenderneſs of conſcience (deſiring to do nothing but what they may have a word for their rule) refuſe the payment of Tythes: But we think it may be ſafer ſaid, that you rob God of his glory, in ſetting your ſelf in the ſeat of God; for by demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Tythes, you take the Prieſthood upon your ſelf, <note place="margin">Heb. 10. from 1. to 15. verſ.</note> which is now ceaſed. Tythes typified the great High-Prieſt of our ſoules Chriſt Jeſus, who hath by one offering put an end to all Sacrifices and Prieſthood; and hath alſo paid the debt that was due for ſin; how then can we rob God, except it be of his glory? For matter of debt, he is fully ſatisfied; but if it had been before the time of our delivery by Chriſt, and we had been Jews, and you had been of the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> and ordained to ſerve at the Altar, then, under that diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if we had not paid you Tythes, you muſt have ſaid, that we had robbed God: But the Lord be praiſed, thoſe dayes of bondage are ended: Oh that the Lord would open your hearts, and convince your conſciences of this your blind zeal! But we ſhall leave this your raſh cenſure, and reply further, in that you plead <hi>accuſtomed rates ſet upon houſes which have been paid time out of mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We demand firſt, whether you are ignorant of the time when it began, that Tythes were firſt impoſed upon the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants by the Landlord? We fear your great predeceſſor, the Man of ſin, and the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> were the firſt inſtitutors of that ſuperſtitions Idol, as impoſition of Tythes, who teach for doctrines the traditions of men, and ſo make the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God of none effect by their traditions, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.6, 7.</p>
            <p>Secondly, What reaſon have you to plead antient cuſtome, when as you live under the Goſpel, and ſay you are labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers in the word and doctrine; of what? of the Law? then indeed you may urge cuſtome from antiquity; but if of the Goſpel, why not a Goſpel-precept? But we blame you not to ſeek to blind the eys of the ignorant by your antient cuſtoms. What greater arguments have the Jeſuites, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their corrupt principles, then Antiquity? as if men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel ſeek for rules elſwhere then the Word of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64968:8"/>God: But we fear that the love of money hath blinded your eys, that you cannot ſee, or diſcover the true meaning of that which the Apoſtle meaneth, that <hi>they which preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel;</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.14. though the Apoſtle uſed it not, but rather laboured with his hands: But why ſhould we ſpeak of laboring w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> the hands, ſo long as you plead the law &amp;cuſtoms of men? for then you have ſtrength enough on your ſide: but god is to be obeyed before men. But to leave this; While God ſhall put it into the hearts of our Rulers, to ſearch whether or no this ancient Law and Cuſtome hath its foundation from the Goſpell, which is and ought, and (we hope, thorough Gods mercy, ever ſhall be our rule. But now to come to the Reaſons you alledge to maintain your Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> Firſt you ſay, <hi>It is a breach of the eighth Commandement, which ſaith,</hi> Thou ſhalt not ſteal: <hi>and directly contrary to the rule of the Apostle,</hi> Rom. 13.7. <hi>Render therfore to all thier dues, tribute to whom tribute is due,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> You think you have ſomthing now on your ſide, but pray conſider, whether or no the Apoſtle ſpeaks there concerning Tithes; his junction is for paying of tribute, which might lawfully be required by a civill power or Authority, and in ſuch things there is no tie on the conſcience, or ſnare, by which it is intrapped; but, as our Saviour commanded, that what was <hi>Caeſar's</hi> one ſhould be paid or given unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 22.21</note> which is all one to thoſe accuſtomed aſſeſments or rates now ſet on men, by thoſe that God hath ſet in authority: And look in the verſes foregoing your text, they are ſuch <hi>Powers as are ordained by God,</hi> and are <hi>Ministers for God to miniſter ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice:</hi> But what is this argument or reaſon of any force to prove the lawfulneſs of paying Tythes to Miniſters under the Goſpell? But you poſitively affirm, <hi>That the Miniſter hath, by the Law of God, as legall a right to the rates ſet upon houſes, as the Landlord hath to his rend;</hi> which we deny abſolutely; for according to your former argument, <hi>time out of mind,</hi> the Landlords had Law for their rent, or a right to their rent by Law, before ever Law was made for paying of Tythes to Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, except you will prove the antiquity of your Law,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64968:8"/>from God's injunction of the children of Iſrael to pay tythes of all they poſſeſſed: And again, the Landlord hath more right to his rent then you have to tythes, for many Landlords have right to their lands and houſes by inheritance, but you have but a bare right from a humane inſtitution, and that by a Law not as yet aboliſhed by the State now in being.</p>
            <p>But if we ſhould grant, as we cannot, except you ſhew bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reaſon then your bare poſitive affirmation, that it is as lawfull for the one, as for the other: Yet wee wonder, you have no proofe of Scripture for your argument, knowing, or rather having ought to have knowne, that it is the onely rule, whereby the people of God ought to walk: Therefore we conclude, that it is no breach of the eighth commandement, inſomuch as no command of God is broken; and to charge the non-payment of tythes to be theft, we know not how you can make it good, except you prove a right, or that you have a right by the Law of God, to the money, or ware, or what els we do enjoy.</p>
            <p>But you add further, that <hi>it is a breach of the Law of God,</hi> and that you would prove in the anſwer to the firſt objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is <hi>that to pay tythes is antichriſtian, therefore not to be paid any longer,</hi> which you call a <hi>falſe opinion,</hi> and would make it appear by this argument ot yours, viz. <hi>That which our Saviour enjoyned is not antichriſtian, but our Saviour enjoyned tythes,</hi> Luke 11.42. <hi>Ye tythe Mini, Rue, and all manner of herbs, and paſſe over iudgment and the love of God; theſe ought ye to have done;</hi> that is, ſay you, <hi>ye ought to pay tythes, therfore they are not antichriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We deſire that you will again conſider this Scripture, both the perſon ſpeaking, and the perſons ſpoken unto; here is Chriſt by way of reprehenſion reprowing the Phariſees for their formality, and pretending to make conſcience of the ſmalleſt matters, when the chiefeſt and weightieſt things of the Law were neglected by them; <hi>Woe to you Phariſees, for ye tythe mint, &amp;c.</hi> And we know that the Phariſees were Jewes and unbelievers, therefore as yet not freed from the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall Law. Therefore it was a Law to them, and requiſite for them to fulfill, but we hope you will not affirm, that this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64968:9"/>was Chriſts Injunction to the Diſciples, or to thoſe that believe that Chriſt is come in the fleſh; for the Apoſtle ſaid, that whoſoever was circumciſed; was bound to keep the Law; and even ſo denies that Chriſt is come in the fleſh.</p>
            <p>Therefore if Tythes be alſo a ceremoniall right or precept, it holds forth (as was ſaid before) that the thing ſignified being come, the ſign is ended. For Circumciſion and Tythes waſhing, and purifyings are held out by the Holy Ghoſt in the 9. of the <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> to continue but to the time of reformation; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we deny poſitively that Tythes were by Chriſt enjoyned to believers; and then if you have no ſtronger argument to prove that Tythe is the Injunction of Chriſt, either by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept or example from him, or from the Apoſtles for believers to obſerve, we cannot be evinced by that which you inferre from that in the 11. of <hi>Luke</hi> 42. <hi>v.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then of neceſſity the objection ſtands firm, and not yet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrown, or proved a falſe opinion, to wit, that to pay Tythes to Miniſters of the Goſpell is Anti-chriſtian; for what is not for, or with Chriſt, is againſt Chriſt; but to pay Tythes, is not for, or with Chriſt: <hi>Ergo</hi> Anti-chriſtian.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> Again, whereas you proceed in your anſwer to the ſecond objection; <hi>but we do not come to hear him, why then ſhould we pay him, ſince we have no benefit by his Ministery?</hi> Your an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is, <hi>If thou live in a Pariſh where a godly Miniſter is ſeated, thou art bound to hear him, for he worketh the work of the Lord, as well as thoſe of greater parts,</hi> 1 Cor. 16.10. <hi>If thou doe not hear him, nor pay him, thou addest ſin to ſin; firſt it is a ſin to withdraw thy preſence, and then it is another, yea a greater, to withdraw his maintenance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now you go about; firſt, to inſinuate not only the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of your own calling to be a Miniſter of the Goſpel truly called, &amp;c. by gifts and parts which God hath endued men withall.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, you lay alſo an Injunction upon all in the Pariſh wherein you are ſeated, to come and hear you, by the charge you lay of committing two ſins, the withdrawing the preſence, and the withdrawing your maintenance.</p>
            <p>But for the firſt argument, we conceive, that as you have
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64968:9"/>not brought any proof of Scripture to prove your calling to be a true Miniſter of the Goſpell; therefore we ſhall not need to raiſe any argument to diſprove you, but ſhall remain deſirous of ſome ſatisfaction in that particular; for though gifts and parts are eſſentiall to a Miniſter of the Goſpell, yet that is but one part of his calling; it is requiſite that he be choſen and ordained by a true Church; for that Scripture which you have brought in the <hi>Corinths</hi> concerning <hi>Timothy</hi> doth in no wiſe prove you to be ſo; then, if no true Miniſter, the force of that argument muſt fall to the ground.</p>
            <p>Secondly, We muſt then be at a loſſe in our anſwer to the inference which you draw, that <hi>living in a Pariſh, we ought to come and hear;</hi> but the Spouſe of Jeſus Chriſt, in the firſt of the <hi>Canticles,</hi> doth inquire for Chriſt's aboad and reſidence, which is, to the <hi>flocks of his companions;</hi> &amp; except you can prove that a Pariſh is a true church, your argument is of no force to draw any to the place of the aſſembling, <hi>for where there is no Law, there is no ſin;</hi> but you have charged ſin, where you can ſhew no Inſtitution; pray, why do not you preach this to be a ſin, to thoſe which live in Pariſhes far diſtant from you, and yet come to hear you, where (for ought you can judge) are godly Miniſters, and yet they leave their owne. Pariſh, and go to hear ſome in one Pariſh, and ſome in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Again, how can that be charged as ſin, for <hi>not coming to hear in the Pariſh wherein they live?</hi> when, as in the firſt place, their tender conſciences cannot eat or drink with thoſe that are not as yet ſeparated, and come out of the world, and joyned in a church fellowſhip, and therefore where there is no Union there can be no Communion. Secondly, though they may live in your Pariſh, yet the aſſembly whereof they are members, meet two or three Pariſhes off, and in the rule of equity how can you judge theſe ſinners, that goe out of your Pariſh to heare for their further edification and growth in the knowiedge of Chriſt, in obediedce to the rule of the Apoſtle, not forſaking the aſſembling themſelves together, as the manner of ſome is; but with whom? <note place="margin">Heb. 10.25.</note> with the Church where Chriſt hath promiſed his preſence, as that, <hi>where two or three are gathered together in his Name, he wil be in the midst of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64968:10"/>them;</hi> but mind, we pray you, it muſt be in his Name, that is, according to his example in the order of the Goſpell, not with <hi>Babylon,</hi> which ſignifies <hi>[a confuſion of mixture]</hi> from whence the people of God are to come out. <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.17.</note> Again, If Chriſts preſence be with his people ſo met together, then where ſhould they go but there? <note place="margin">Rev. 18.4.</note> and out of ſuch a people are Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and. Teachers to be choſen, who have the teachings of the Spirit of God, accompanied with the knowledge of the word of God, which is able to make the <hi>man of God perfect, thoroughly furniſhed unto all good works,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.17. Theſe are thoſe Shepheards that come in at the right door, ſpoken of in the tenth of <hi>John,</hi> whoſe voice, thoſe which are ſheep, wil hear, but thoſe which are thieves, and robbers, or ſtrangers, which come in by other wayes, theſe they will not heare. But you ſay, <hi>where a godly Miniſter is ſeated, there we ought to heare:</hi> But pray tell us, whether God and <hi>Beliall</hi> can live to gether, how came you by that Miniſteriall Office? had it not its riſe from the Biſhops and Prelates, and they their riſe from the Pope? and though you have put on a faire gloſſe, and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to your ſelves of late the name of <hi>Presbyters,</hi> have you yet openly denied the other, ſo as to have diſclaimed that Ordination by which you ſtand? is not the ſame language of the Beaſt ſounded forth from your mouths, as proceeded from the mouth of the firſt Beaſt? did you not ſhew your ſelves bitter againſt thoſe that could not ſubmit to what you had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon in the Claſſicall Aſſembly? and when you had the power in your hands, did you not vex, moleſt, and impriſon the Saints of God? and how far might your blind zeale have tranſported you, had you not been ſtrucken down by a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hand? but bleſſed be God, the great Reformer, whoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection is far better, and gives more light into his will, then all the Presbyterian Directory could do; therefore ſend us not, we beſeech you, to the <hi>Directory,</hi> but to the <hi>word of God;</hi> but however we are by you judged or cenſured for not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to hear you, yet you will not judge them that come a mile or two to hear you, ſooth them up in their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
            <p>Again, you make the forbearance of paying you Tythes.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64968:10"/>to be <hi>a greater ſinne, then the not hearing of the Word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We even bluſh to hear you; but it is true, covetouſneſſe will ſtretch the judgement many times to great and large ſins, as well of Error, as of Practiſe; had you not by your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per diſcovered ſo much groſſe, and almoſt unparallel'd and abſurd hypocriſie, which makes us even tremble to read it, we ſhould not have beene ſo preſſed in our Spirit to enter upon theſe replies; and we hope the Lord in his time, (as he hath) ſo he will more diſcover the hypocriſie of your bitter hearts againſt thoſe tender conſciences that dare not yeeld obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to that Law, as yet not taken away by the power now in being; but we hope the Lord will give them eyes to ſee the great oppreſſion that lyeth upon the Nation in that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. But to proceed, pray conſider what you have affirmed to make the non-payment of Tythes a <hi>greater ſin, then the not hearing the Word of God.</hi> Conſider (we pray) the effects of hearing the word of God, is it not the meanes by which Faith is begotten in the heart, (as ſaith the Apoſtle in the to. of the <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.) and whereby knowledge is encreaſed, eſpecially, when thoſe declare it that are the true diſpenſators of the Word of God; and certainly if your love were more for the gaining of poor ſouls, then it is unto money, which is the root of all evill, you would be of another mind, and follow the example of the <note n="*" place="margin">Acts 20.33, 34, 35.1 Cor. 9.18.</note> Apoſtle <note n="†" place="margin">Who without queſtion did mind the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Saviour <hi>Mat. 10.8,</hi> 9. verſe <hi>Freely ye have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, freely give</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Paul,</hi> which would rather work with his hands then be chargeable to the Churches; and if your tongues were touched with a coal from Gods Altar, as was <hi>Iſayas,</hi> the Prophets, you would then be of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother mind; but the Lord open your eyes, that if by any meanes you may ſee the hardneſſe of your hearts. But we have learned better of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, then to be of your judgment in that particular. What mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is it that you mean? is it Tythes? that is cleare to be the wages of the Prieſt that ſerved at the Altar; But that hath been handled already: and now we are not to look back to the Law for our rule, nor to the <hi>Directory</hi> made by your Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly; For if an Angell from heaven were to declare us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other rule, then the doctrine which our Lord and Saviour
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64968:11"/>hath taught us, we are commanded to eſchew it, &amp;c. But tythes are not the inſtitution of Chriſt (as you falſſy affirm) for believers to obſerve, therefore on ſin: but to heare, is the command of God; <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.5. <hi>This is my beloved Son, hear him.</hi> Therefore not to hear, is a great ſin, and we hope any judicious man which is of your own judgment, will ſay a greater, then the non-payment of tythes.</p>
            <p>But for the third Objection which you have anſwered, <hi>viz. But the Miniſter will not give us our due in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper; therfore we may iuſtly deny him his due.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This indeed may by ſome of your Pariſhioners be objected, who out of blind zeal may ſuppoſe they have a right to that Goſpel-Ordinance, when they have not; and where it is not to be had: And whereas you bring that Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order;</hi> you may know there the Apoſtle ſpeaks of <hi>prophecying one by one,</hi> and therein order and decency ought to be obſerved, yet not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining the liberty of any from ſpeaking, but being a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of a true Church, and gifted by the Spirit of God, he may ſpeak to edification. <hi>The Apoſtle did not monopolize the work of the Miniſtery;</hi> but exhorted all the Church to covet to propheſie, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.31.39.</note> and ſaith, <hi>Ye may all propheſie one by one;</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> wiſhed <hi>all the Lords people were Prophets:</hi> But to come to your anſwer, <note place="margin">Numb. 11 29.</note> ſeeing this Scripture makes not for your purpoſe in that particular, whereas you hold forth to the eye of the world, that you would do nothing but what may be according to the order of the Goſpel. We ſhould have liked your argument well, if you would have declared an order from the Goſpell for tythes: but if you cannot prove from the Goſpel your practiſe, you will (like thoſe who are ready to ſink) catch hold of a ſtraw to keep your head above water; you will run to the lawes of man, ſo from humane precepts infer Goſpel-inſtitutions: So you bring the vindication of the Presbyterian Government as undeniable, to prove your examining of perſons: But what rule have you from the Goſpel for this your practice, that we muſt ſearch mens works and leave the Word of God, which is the onely means of ſalvation. Our Saviour ſends the Jews to <hi>ſearch the Seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures;</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:64968:11"/>not any learned Father, or Treatiſe made by Synods. The <hi>Bereans</hi> would not receive the doctrines, or teachings of the Apoſtles, before they had ſearched in the Word of God, to know <hi>whether thoſe things were ſo or no,</hi> for which they were called <hi>more noble then thoſe of Theſſalonica;</hi> but as it hath been held forth by the <hi>See of Rome;</hi> that <hi>Ignorance is the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Devotion:</hi> See if you can perſwade men to believe the worſhip you hold forth, as to pay Tythes, and come to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined by a few ignorant men, <hi>(ſuch who are choſen many times for your Elders)</hi> who have more need of examination themſelves oftentimes, then many poor ſouls, which you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar from that, which you call the Supper of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Again, we wonder you are not aſhamed to charge us with ſcandalous ſins, as to tearm us <hi>Thieves and Robbers,</hi> and that <hi>of God;</hi> but we hope your Kingdome is falling, and now ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your time is ſhort, you begin to rage with open mouth, yet all you can ſay will not adde one day to your continuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, you have not in the leaſt proved your ſelves Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, neither have you proved a command from God to pay Tythes, how then can you call us robbers; you learn not theſe raſh cenſures of the Apoſtle, who was free in the diſpenſation of the Goſpell, and thirſted more after the gaining of poore ſouls to the knowledge of the truth, then after their moneys or inheritance: it was not Tythes, or great living that open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their mouths, but love to the promulgation of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Jeſus Chriſt, where is there that love in any of you, that will rather leave whole Pariſhes deſtitute of meanes, we mean of that which you call labouring in the Goſpell) and ſeek for greater livings? Is this the right doore by which a true Paſtor ought to come into the ſheepfold? but you are ratther indeed right <hi>thieves</hi> and <hi>robbers,</hi> which rob not onely God of his glory, by attributing to your ſelves the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, but you alſo rob the people; Firſt, of their ſouls bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, which they might receive from a true Miniſter: Secondly, of their moneys, to which you have no right by the Law of God. How many poor men are there in this Nation, that <hi>groane under the great bondage of Tythes,</hi> who have not ſo much as wil maintain their own charge with their great pains
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64968:12"/>and induſtry, and you will rack the tythe of all their labour the whole yeare, and alſo of the fruit thereof, think you not that the cry of this oppreſſing ſin doth cry for vengeance; and certainly the avenger of bloud will in his time avenge their cauſe; and when that falſe Prophet ſpoken of <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20. is taken, he ſhall with all his falſe Teachers be judged; and think you, that then the <hi>Tythe-hunters</hi> ſhall eſcape? what are their deſerts we dare not judge, though you are ſo raſh as to judge poor tender conſciences to hell fire. Further to proceed to the third reaſon, and to examine what weight or ſhew of truth is in it, for the former, he that hath but an eye of reaſon may diſcerne, that covetouſneſſe hath ſo choaked them of your judgement, that truth cannot be received by them.</p>
            <p>Your third reaſon, <hi>It is a complicated ſin, wherein fraud or cheating is added to theft, for the Landlord lets his houſe to the Tenant upon this accompt, namely, that he ſhall pay the duties to the Minister: As for example, if the houſe be worth</hi> 21. <hi>l.</hi> per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, <hi>the Landlord lets is for</hi> 20. <hi>l.</hi> per annum, <hi>on purpoſe perhaps that the Tenant may pay</hi> 20.5. <hi>to the Miniſter</hi> per annum, <hi>the Tenant notwithſtanding payes nothing, but keeps it back from the Miniſter by frand, and puts the Landlonds money into his owne yocket, here is frand with a Witneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here take notice how you charge a duplicated ſin, we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feffe if you were, as you look upon your ſelves to be, a true Teacher of Inſtructer of a people, it were your duty to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them, and dehort them from any known ſin, which they live or continue in; but if the foregoing reaſons, with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, have no force to prove the non-payment of tythes to be a ſinne, then of neceſſity this aggravating reaſon, or coneluſion, muſt in like manner fall to the ground.</p>
            <p>For our parts we are ſo far from conceiving it a ſinne of ſuch a nature, that we ſhould ſin in ſo ſaying: But to come home to your reaſon, tearming it <hi>acheat, or defrauding,</hi> pray what is your intention, in that you ſay <hi>they defraud?</hi> Firſt you ſay, it is <hi>the Landlords money that he puts in his pocket, though it was the Landlords intention he ſhould pay the Miniſter his due:</hi> Firſt, this is that which ever before we were ignorant of, but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64968:12"/>if it be as you affirm, the Landlord muſt alſo comply with the Parſon, and ſo are both, as <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi, brethren in evill;</hi> and what do you elſe then defraud the poor Tenant? by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnaring of him to do that which is a direct ſin againſt his light, and do (as much as in you lye) cauſe him to deny Chriſt come in the fleſh, in impoſing upon him a ceremoniall Law. which were all one, as if you would teath Circumciſion and burnt Offering; but as the Apoſtle demanded in <hi>Gal. 3. who had bewitched them from the love of the truth?</hi> So may we ſay, who hath bewitched you, <hi>O ye fooliſh Presbyterian Priests?</hi> that you are ſo fallen into ſuch a contrariety to truth, that is that which God hates, for men to halt between two opinions: If the worſhip of Chriſt be to be obſerved? If he be Lord of all, let him be Lord? but if the ceremoniall Law be that which is now our rule, then let us have Prieſts, and Levites, and burne Offerings, and Sacrifices: are theſe the Reformers of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that ſeek by their <hi>Directory</hi> to deſude the Nation, and briing them into a greater bondage then ever the Iſraelites were? That after the profeſſion of the glorious Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſt, (which makes men Chriſts free men) to be inſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved again into bondage, and moreover to enact Lawes, Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions and Ordinances of men, to inforce the conſciences of men; and if that will not do, to ſet <hi>Promoters</hi> on their backs, and to impriſon men, and ſeize on their goods, and take them by force; is not this <hi>theft</hi> and <hi>defrauding</hi> (as we may ſay) <hi>with a Witneſſe?</hi> But we hope thoſe that are entruſted with <hi>Englands Liborty,</hi> will ſhortly ſee and take notice of this great bondage of the Commons, we mean the poor country people, who have ſo much ſuffered in this behalfe, and yet have had no redreſſe, and alſo the inſulting cruelty of thoſe bſoundy Prieſts or Presbyters, that (like <hi>Meroz) came not out on to help the Lord againſt the mighty;</hi> but when they did ſee their <hi>Dagon</hi> was like to fall, together with Reg all Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, laid all their heads together to uphold that power, which the Lord had determined to overthrow; and whileſt they were ſee to be fighters againſt God, he took of their Chariot wheels that they drove heavily, and were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, as <hi>Pharoah</hi> and his Hoſt; yet the Lord ſuffers them
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64968:13"/>a little while, if by any means they would ſee the deceipt and hypocriſie of their hearts; and if this writing will not work its kindly effects, then let them take heed of the woe that is coming forht againſt them, and that this laſt ſnare prove not a greater overthrow to their Kingdome then the firſt: This one thing we heartily deſire, that God would pleaſe to let them ſee this the errour of their hearts, before the great judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment fall down upon them: but we ſhall leave, and come to the fourth reaſon you give.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is a ſin whereby godly Ministers are diſcouraged in their work, their hands weakned, and their Spirits broken, ſo that they cannot go on in their Miniſtery with joy, but with grief. This is directly contrary to that godly King</hi> Hezekiah, <hi>whoſe example is written for our learning,</hi> Rom. 15.4. <hi>for it is teſtified of him,</hi> 2 Cron. 31.4. <hi>that he commanded the people that dwelt in Hiern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalew, to give t he portion of the Priests, and the Levites, thay they might be incouraged in the Law of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the world may take notice of your zeal ion the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Goſpell, whether it be not covetouſneſſe that ſteers you in all your proceedings, you cannot forget the Gardlick and Onyons, which was the food of the children of Iſrael, which made them grumble and murmure againſt God, and againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> by which their hearts were enfeebled; and it is now the great diſeaſe moſt of you are troubled withall, as the French ſaying is, (<hi>fault d' Argent,</hi> want of money.) Now your great benefices are taken away, by which many of your Lords waxed wanton.</p>
            <p>Now the great complaint is, <hi>want of maintenance,</hi> and therefore you cry out, <hi>The work of the Lord goeth ſlowly on:</hi> but we hope by this time you will be aſhamed to aſſume to your ſelves the names of Prieſts and Levites, but by the inferences you draw, you make people believe no leſſe, by reaſon that all the refuge you have to fly unto for the maintenance of tythes is to the ceremoniall Law, as in that place noted by you, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 31.4. The exhortation of the King <hi>Hezekiah</hi> to the people, <hi>to give the portion to the Prieſts and Levites to encourage them:</hi> Firſt, conſider, as we have before declared that this portion was their wages for their work, but it is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64968:13"/>with Goſpell Miniſters; what wages had the Diſciples, when they were ſent from Chriſt to declare the grace of God in Juſes Chriſt? what was there any condition made for wages or hire? <hi>John</hi> 10. <hi>The Mireling in no good Shepheard,</hi> as by ſad experience hath been found in all that are called Chriſtian Nations, &amp; how came they in, but over hedges and by-wayes, and inſtead of <hi>laying down their live; for the ſheep, they have devoured them:</hi> But you will ſay, <hi>the labon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer is worthy of his hire?</hi> pray what did the Diſciples want, when they returned? could not the Goſpell yeeld its en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, as well in the gaining ſoules to God, as alſo in the maintenance of them that work in the harveſt? therefore you have no warrant to uſe unlawfull means to come by mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, as tythes, which is altogether <hi>unlawfull and Anti-Chriſtian,</hi> and that which doth extinguiſh the light of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>Again, this your argument muſt of neceſſity unvaile much of the falſeneſſe of the hearts of thoſe Miniſters, that make the non-payment of tythes to be alone wheel that moves their Zeal for the publication of Goſpell, and the bloud that moves in the veins, by which they are made ſtong in the work of the Miniſtery; for by withholding of tythes they are weakned in the work, and their ſpirirs cannot act, and ſo are become dumb; theſe are ſad ſoul-Phyſitians, that though the poor ſouls are like to famiſh for want of ſpririuall food, they may famiſh and periſh if they have not wherewithall to give them the tythes they demand, like ſome Phyſitians, which will have their money in hand, though in the meane time the Patient is like to periſh for want of their help: But you ſay they are diſcouraged by want of tythes, which is their main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance; ſurely well they may, when as they ſhall ſeek their maintenauce in an unwarrantable way, having no Goſpell precept for in: Nor doe judge that there is any cauſe of diſcouragement, or rather that they ſhould complaine that they are diſcouraged for not being maintained by an errour, and ſuch an errour, as even amounts to hereſie it ſelfe, for what greater hereſie can there be, then to deny Chriſt come im the fleſh? but the inforeing of Cireumciſion, Tythes, with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64968:14"/>the ſervices and rights of the Leviticall Law, doth extend ſo far as to the denying Chriſts coming in the fleſh; therefore pray do not think to draw us ever a whit the more to be of your opinion in that particular of tythes, or the lawfullneſſe of it, becauſe the non-payment thereof is a diſcouragement to your preaching, or a weakning to your ſpirits; we could wiſh that this diſcouragement would work your hearts into an humble frame, or temper, then you would not cry ſo outragiouſly againſt the Saints and ſervants of God, which are ſo kept by his power, as not to ſubmit to your wayes and worſhip for not paying of tythes: It is not <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, as you infer, to the people that were under the Liviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, as you infer, to the people that were under the Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Law, that can be any example for our practiſe of paying of tythes for you rencouragement: And concerning the Juſtice of God, whereas you ſay, It is juſt with God to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw his bleſſing, by reaſon we cannot pay tythes for your maintenance;</p>
            <p>We may juſtly ſay it is juſt with God to draw his bleſſing from your end eavours, and that upon good ground, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that you go on in an illegall way, contrary to precept or example to urge that as your due, which never was, and to preſſe it ſo hard on the conſciences of any, ſo that you have intrapped multitudes into your ſnares and gins: but this be ſure, that inſtead of a bleſſing your ſpeak of, you may fear the contrary, leaſt that the curſe of God will light upon you, and all your proceedings, that ſeek to d<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hrone the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and to ſet up your own power, and to nullifie his Lawes, and to enact the <hi>Law of Moſes,</hi> or rather the <hi>Law of men;</hi> but as the foundation of that Law is ſandy, having no more weight but <hi>antient cuſtome,</hi> as you falſely aſſume, <hi>time our of mind,</hi> ſo the fall of it will be great, when your ſins are ripened, and the time is come of your downfall, and then your grieſe will be more and more encereaſed. But now we ſhall proceed to your fifth reaſon, to examine what weight that hath whereby to work forth our conſciences to this point of yours, concerning the <hi>payment of tythes to Miniſters of the Goſpell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reaſ. <hi>It is a ſin</hi> (ſay you) <hi>wherein, and whereby the deſrauder robs
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64968:14"/>his own ſould of that ſpirituall benefit and advantage, which he might get by ſuch a Ministery, for it is juſt with God go ſay to ſuch a man, thou withdraweſt maintenance from ſervant, and I will withdraw my bleſſing from my own Ordinance, ſo that the word preached, by whomſoever it is diſpenſed, ſhall do thee no good at all but rather it ſhall be a ſavour of death to thy own condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, thy ſoul ſhall never proſper or thrive by any Sermon thou heareſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We admire to ſee or hear from any man ſuch raſh inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate cenſures, when as our Lord and Maſter Chriſt Juſus hath leſt us ſuch a warning piece in <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. <hi>Judge not leaſt thou, beest judges.</hi> For matter of fraud or cheating, we think we have ſufficiently proved the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> we mean the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Prieſts are the greateſt defranders,</hi> therefore we ſhall not now touch any further upon that, but to ſhew in this particular your cunning cautelous wiles, wherein you lye in Wait to deceice. But we are exhorted <hi>not to-let any man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile us.</hi> We hope the Lord will ſtill ſupport us with the aſſiſtance of his Spirit to diſcern all your wiles, and eſpecially this of your <hi>injunction of Tythes.</hi> But you go about to fright us with the <hi>juſtice of God,</hi> and you meaſure Gods Juſtice, which is an attribute in himſelf (unchangeable) by the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of men, who are mutable; in this you ſhew a great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption to meddle with Gods Juſtice, but in this you are raſh and cenſorious, as in all the reſt of your reaſons: But for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, we have already proved, that <hi>Tythes are not maintenance for Miniſters under the Goſpell,</hi> but were to Prieſts under the Law; therefore it would be ſin to perform any unlawfull a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, for the maintenance of any, though you were Goſpell Miniſters, but to pay Tythes is unlawfull; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no ſinne to deny the paying thereof, for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Miniſters, for that God hath not commanded, if we make it our duty, though commanded by man, it is <hi>will-worſhip,</hi> as worſhipping of Angells, &amp;c. <hi>coloſ.</hi> 7.18, 19. and God may ſay, <hi>who hath required this at your hands, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa.</hi> 1.12. It is not then our pleading, <hi>Authority commanded us,</hi> will acquit us at that day, thoug <hi>in civill action we ought to be obedient to the Anthority in being;</hi> but tythes was a ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64968:15"/>of the Leviticall Law, as well as Circumciſion, which are both aboliſhed: therefore how can you expect a bleſſing from God upon the work of your Miniſtery, ſo long as you plead for any falſe worſhip; it is all one as if you pleaded for <hi>Baal,</hi> which was idolatry; So tythes being that which is aboliſhed, is now in oppoſition to the Goſpell, therefore ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry and hereſie, which is a <hi>ſin highly diſpleaſing to God:</hi> and for heretiques, <hi>we are not ſo much as to eat withali.</hi> Therefore you may not marvell why you are abandoned by ſo many people whoſe conſciences are tender concerning the worſhip of God, by reaſon that you do maintain a falſe worſhip. But concerning Gods bleſſing, which alwayes accompanies his own Ordinance, many thouſands of this Nation have had great and large experience of: We mean ſuch as are not of the <hi>Presbyterian Order,</hi> but ſuch unto whom God of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite mercy hath made known his truth, and diſcovered the darkneſs of thoſe who would be called <hi>Preſbyterians,</hi> who indeed are zealous (many of them) in their profeſſion; but their zeal is blind in many things, as in this of tythes, which makes them, like <hi>Saul,</hi> to breath out perſecution againſt the Saints, to diſquiet their peaceable being; yea they will take hold of the ſword of the Magiſtrate to proſecute their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes. But, we hope, as the Lord hath overthrown their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes againſt the peace of this Commonwealth, ſo he will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in this great deſigne of diſturbing the peace of his people of this Nation, who are indeed the pillars upon which the ſafety of the Nation lieth, and take away the pillars, the houſe muſt needs fall. <hi>Oh, that the Pareiament would conſider this, and ſtand for the liberty of thoſe that have ſpent their lives and eſtates for the liberty of this Nation, and that God would put it into their hearts to take off all heavy burdens, and even this unſupportable yoke of tythes from this Nation!</hi> Againe, we conceive you have ſomwhat inlarged your ſelf, in ſaying, <hi>by whomſoever it is dispenſed, the word is diſpenſed, but ſhall do thee no good at all, but rather a ſavour of death, &amp;c.</hi> You ſeem here by this argument, to reach all Miniſters, as well true as falſe, and ſo long as the people abſtain from paying tythes to the <hi>Pariſh Prieſt;</hi> beare with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64968:15"/>us, if the title <hi>Prieſt</hi> be put in, (for tythes imply, you appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate Prieſthood to your ſelves) <hi>though they do hear a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter rightly conſtituted, yet no benefit ſhall accrue</hi> (ſay you) <hi>to their ſoules, but on the contrary a curſe,</hi> this is a very ſad and lamentable condition, that ſuch a poor ſoul ſhall be in; we mean that ſuch a man (who thorough tenderneſſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience doth refuſe to pay tythes to the Prieſt that miniſtreth in the Pariſh where he lives) ſhall receive no benefit from whomſoever he heareth.</p>
            <p>But this we abſolutely deny: For firſt of all, if he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe thorough the tenderneſſe of his conſcience (deſiring on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be regulated by the Word) to hear you, he doth well, for <hi>that which is not of faith, is ſin;</hi> and a man ought to be perſwaded of what he believes to be true, and conſequently he doth ſin againſt his conſcience, if he heareth ſuch a one, that goeth about to perſwade, or inforce him to do any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his conſcience, &amp; you teach that to <hi>pay tythes is the duty of believers, both by the Law of God and man, and he believes that to pay tythes,</hi> is a ſin, by reaſon he hath no warrant from the Word for it being a believer.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if ſuch perſon ſhould refrain the hearing of him, that declareth the word or mind of God, as the truth is in Chriſt, according to that light which God hath endowed him withall, certainly he ſhould ſin in an high nature, a ſin of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; and you muſt acknowledge the bleſſing of God doth accompany his own Ordinance; except you hold there is no Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God held forth by any but the <hi>Presbyterian Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,</hi> who preſſe ſo hard for tythes. And thirdly, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence witneſſeth the contrary, how many thouſand poor ſouls have been converted from their natural eſtate by the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſators of the Word, even by thoſe of ſelect Churches, though you may term their converſion ſubverſion, or deluding, yet our experiences witneſſe to us the contrary; therefore the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference you draw muſt needs fall to the ground.</p>
            <p>Your ſixth reaſon is, <hi>That it is a ſin that provokes God to curſe a man in his outward estate and trading,</hi> as you inſtance in that of <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.9. Ye are curſed with a curſe, for ye have robbed, &amp;c. <hi>It is uſuall with God to pay ſinners with their owne
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64968:16"/>co<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, they rob God in tythes, and God robs them of their trade and lively hood; they grudge the Miniſters maintenance, and God e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven grudgeth them bread from their families, ſo that they uſually tu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n bankrupts, or are ſo much in debt, that they are aſhamed to ſhew their faces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have already proved that the non-payment of tythes is not robbing of God, therefore that place is of no force to prove, that believers <hi>rob God by not paying tythes,</hi> but on the contrary, he that payeth tythes doth rob God, by reaſon in that action he doth abet unto the unlawfulneſſe of their practiſe who upheld the Prieſthood of <hi>Aaron</hi> to be ſtill in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when as we own no other Prieſthood then Chriſt Jeſus, that Pretogative alone belongeth to him, then there is no curſe, but rather a bleſſing, by diſowning the unlawfull pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of paying tythes, and conſequently they are bleſſed in their trading.</p>
            <p>But whereas you ſay, <hi>they grudge the Miniſters mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> we believe none that have learned the leſſon of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>thee they which preach the goſpel, ſhall live of the goſpel, and that thoſe which freely ſow in ſpiritualls, ſhould reap of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls,</hi> ſhould grudge a true Miniſter of the Goſpel mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, therefore your charge is too large in that particular alſo; we grudge no mans maintenance; much leſſe ſuch as la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>in the word and doctrine,</hi> and in charity, we judge, that none of the people of God are ſo hard hearted; therefore your conſequence which you raiſe, muſt needs fall; <hi>That that is the reaſon ſo many turn Bankerupts and run in debt,</hi> &amp;c. It were a hard matter to prove that God pays men in their own coyn, in this life, for generally the wicked and ungodly and covetous of this world do thrive, and grow rich, and encreaſe in worldly goods; but on the contrary, many that are ſincere Iſraelites, as <hi>Nathanael,</hi> doe live but meanely in this world.</p>
            <p>But we ſhall proceed to the ſeventh reaſon, in your paper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is a ſin againſt the Goſpel, becauſe it hinders the progreſſe and ſucceſſe of it, for ſuch men do as much as in them lies, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh the light, by taking away the Oyle that foods it. It is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64968:16"/>by that excellent book, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>indication Presh. Gov. page</hi> 81. <hi>That</hi> Julian <hi>the Apoſtate, curſed enemy of Chriſt and his Goſpel, did by taking away tythes do more miſchiefe to the church of God, then all the perſecuting Emperors that were before him; for the perſecutors took away only the Miniſters, and (their bloud was the ſeed of the church) but taking away tythes, took away the Miniſter himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this reaſon of yours you have made out to the world, that the non-payment of tythes is a ſin againſt the Goſpel, therefore becauſe you make it out a ſin of ſo high a nature, we ſhall anſwer your reaſon in the ſeverall parts thereof, and anatomize it in the ſeverall members thereof.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that which is a ſin againſt the Goſpel, muſt be a breach of ſome known inſtitution of Jeſus Chriſt, either in precept, or example, but tythes were never an inſtitution of Jeſus Chriſt for believers to obſerve, therefore no ſin againſt the Goſpel, though you ſay that place in <hi>Luke</hi> 11.42. proves tythes to be an injunction of Chriſt: That place of Scripture, as before is inſerted, fully importeth Chriſts reprehenſion of the Phariſees for being ſtrict in the obſerving of trivial things, and leaving the weightier, as <hi>[of judgement, and the love of God.]</hi> Now from this place you can prove tythes no more the duty of believers, then the former offices of the Law, as Sacrifices and Offerings for ſin by them which were Levites, and ſerved in the Temple and Tabernacle, which are all put to an end by the Sacriſice of Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.11. and the 10. <hi>c.</hi> 9, 10, 11, 12. v.</p>
            <p>But tythes, as was well obſerved by a brother in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell in certain replies heretofore ſet forth by him, are not morall and perpetuall, and now under the Goſpell to be paid or taken, for theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe it calls for the ſetting up of the Jewiſh Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, tabernacle, and altar, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe it calls for the Prieſthood of <hi>Aaron</hi> and the Levites in their former office to ſerve.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, becauſe it layes a yoke of bondage upon him that pays his tythes, and upon him that takes tythes, which the Goſpell ſets at liberty; and how dare any man charge that to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64968:17"/>be a ſin againſt Goſpell, when we <hi>ſtand faſt to the liberty wherewith Christ hath made us free, Gal.</hi> 5. 1. <hi>v.</hi> Therefore it is your groſſe erronious opinion to charge the non-payment of tythes to Goſpel Miniſters to be <hi>a ſin,</hi> yea and <hi>a Goſpel ſin;</hi> yet we hope this your raſh cenſure ſhall not <hi>bewitch us</hi> to be <hi>withdrawn from the love of the truth,</hi> or to obſerve Leviticall ceremonies for Goſpel Ordinances therefore the non-pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of tythes is no <hi>Goſpel ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly neither doth the non-payment of tythes hinder the progreſſe of the Goſpel, by reaſon that the Goſpel is not furthered in its progreſſe by any unlawfull practiſe, as hath been ſufficiently proved; therefore no let or hinderance, but rather the contrary; for the obſervation of any Levitical ceremony doth extinguiſh the light of the Goſpel, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer uently it doth hinder the progreſſe thereof, And here pray take notice of your abſurdity in this particular, as if tythes were that which would be any furtherance to the progreſſe of the Goſpel; we confeſſe it may be a hinderance of <hi>your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe in your Miniſtery,</hi> and of the ſucceſſe thereof, but no hinderance of thoſe that are true Goſpel Miniſtes, neither of the ſucceſſe of it.</p>
            <p>Again, have you any ground for this reaſon from any of the Apoſtles? When was the Goſpel ſo free in its progreſſe as in the Apoſtles time, who taught us, that the Ceremoniall Law was aboliſhed, and tythes being part of the Ceremoniall Law, if that comes in being again, it muſt needs hinder the ſucceſſe and progreſſe of the Goſpel: Therefore of neceſſity that part of your reaſon muſt needs fall to the ground, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not ſo much as the face of truth to uphold it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In that you ſay, <hi>ſuch men do, as much as in them lies, extinguiſh the light, by taking away the oyle that feeds it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we do alſo admire at the weakneſs of your argument, to make <hi>tythes to be the oyle, that gives light to the Goſpel;</hi> But to the firſt we anſwer, on the contrary, that ſuch men do as much as in them lies, diſcover the true Goſpel-light from that darkneſs and obſcurity which tythes would ſhadow the light of the Goſpel withall, by unvailing it from that, which Chriſt hath put an end unto, we mean all ceremoniall Rights,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64968:17"/>&amp;c. But pray what light is it you mean? Is it the light of your underſtanding (which in this particular is already dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened, therfore cannot be extinguiſhed) or the light of the Goſpel, which is the light of truth? but by your foregoing reaſon, we conceive rather the later; if then, obſerve that is is by this light out eye are in lightened, to diſcover the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this opinion, that, <hi>The non-payment of tythes doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh the light of the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, whereas your inference is, that it <hi>takes away the oyle that feedth it;</hi> we anſwer do you count tythes, or the payment thereof the <hi>oyle that feeds the light of the Goſpel?</hi> Pray, was that the oyle the foolſh virgins lacked, ſo that their lamps went out? We think rather it is the Spirit of God, which giveth light to the Goſpel, and this lieth beyond the reach of any man to take away; We read of many oyles in Scripture, as the <hi>annoiting oyle,</hi> &amp;c. and the <hi>oyle</hi> wherewith Chriſt was annoyted, even <hi>the oyle of gladneſſe above his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows;</hi> but we never yet read that tythes were called by the name of <hi>oyle,</hi> nay ſuch <hi>oyle, as feeds the light of the Goſpel.</hi> Pray when was the light of the Goſpel more darkeded, then when the Biſhops of our later dayes had ſo many ſpirituall livings, or <hi>tythe oyle,</hi> as you call it? Did that oyle which they had in ſuch abundance add anything to the light of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel? Nay rather, did it not ſuffocate it? So now may we truly ſay of you that are <hi>Prieſts of tythe,</hi> by impoſing or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of tythes, ye do (as much as in you his) take away the true <hi>oyle</hi> that feeds this light, by reaſon that you do not diſcover the ſpirituall ſenſe and meaning of the Goſpel, but cloud the glorious light of it, by re-edifying of the Leviticall ceremony of Tythes.</p>
            <p>But we ſhall take a view of that ſaying of yours concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>fulian the Apoſtate,</hi> who (by your affirmation) <hi>did more harm by taking away tythes, then the perſecuting Emperors did by taking away of the Miniſters.</hi> If you have no ſtronger argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prove his Apoſtate then the bare taking away of tythes, the cannot in that be proved an Apoſtate: but if he did this action from a right principle, he was more a friend to the profeſſion of the Goſpel then an enemy: and we hope
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64968:18"/>and heartily with, that the <hi>Parliament of this Commonwealth</hi> would unburthen this Nation from this ſuperſtitious ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of tythes. O that the profit, which the firſt fruits and tythes do yeeld were not ſo much eſteemed by them, as to make it an hinderance of their proceedings in this partitular! It is very obſervable that many of the <hi>Kings of Iſrael did that which was right in the ſight of the Lord;</hi> yet this is charged upon them, that the <hi>high places were not taken down,</hi> untill God raiſed up that <hi>good King Joſiah,</hi> who pulled them down to the ground, and burned the bones of them that offered ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices on them: but we hope there are many amongſt our Worthies, we mean thoſe of the Parliament and Arny, whom God in his time will make like unto <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> who ſhall root up this grand idol of <hi>impoſition of tythes,</hi> which ſo blaſphemouſly is called <hi>the oyle that feeds the light of the Goſpel.</hi> Therfore we hope by this time you may ſee clearly, that the <hi>non-payment of tythes doth not hinder the progreſſe of the Goſpel;</hi> but on the contrary, doth further it: For, if the intruding enemies of the Goſpel, we mean thoſe falſe teachers ſpoken of by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Galat.</hi> 3. did <hi>bewitch them from the love of the truth,</hi> by urging of Circumciſion, and the obſervation of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall Law (which made the Apoſtle fear, he had <hi>laboured in vain, foraſmuch as Christ was not yet formed in them</hi>) then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the urging of the neceſſity of paying tythes, doth hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the free progreſſe of the Goſpel, and eclipſe the light of it, and keeps a poor ſoul under that <hi>Schoolmaſter</hi> which was <hi>to bring us to Chriſt;</hi> but now Chriſt is revealed, he is <hi>the end of the law for righ couſneſſe to every one that believeth,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently no longer need of that to be our Schoolmaſter.</p>
            <p>But in your laſt Reaſon your cry may well be called outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, as if you were bereft of your ſenſes, <hi>It is ſin that will not he pardoned upon repentance, unleſſe there be a reſtitution as well as repentance; according to that of</hi> Auguſtine. Non remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titua peccatum, niſi reſtituatur ablatum: <hi>Thy ſin ſhall not be pardoned, unleſſe that which thou with-holdeſt unjustly be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We know our Saviour faith, that all <hi>ſin and blaſphemy ſhall be forgiven unto men ſave the blaſphemy againſt the Holy Ghoſt,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:64968:18"/>and ſuch a one certainly that ſinneth that unpardonable ſin, hath his heart ſhut up from repentance; and a ſin committed againſt God is of a higher nature then any ſin againſt man, but in all that thou have ſaid, you cannot prove the non-pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of tythe to be a ſin, but on the contrary, we have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it to be a in to pay tythes, and conſequently the non-pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of tythes cannot lay any ſuch burthen upon the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of any man, as to make your reaſon in this particular of any force; but you may well be compared to the Scribes and Phariſees, which laid heavy burthens upon mens ſhoulds, and would not feel the weight of them themſelves. Again, if this your Argument ſhould ſtand, that any may hath unjuſtly with-holden your right or due, we hope you wll grant, that many times God gives a man a heart to repent when he hath not wherewithall to make reſtitution. But we never read of any ſin to be unpardonable, except it was the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, but the non-pryment of tythes cannot be proved a ſin, much leſſe of that nature. Then on the contrary, if (as hath been ſufficiently proved) that to demand tythes under the diſpenſation of the Goſpel by any that are Goſpel-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, or pretend ſo to be, is a ſin againſt the Goſpel, for tythes were never injoyned by our Saviour for believers to obſerve, and to preſume to make an injunction for any duty, where there is no precept nor example, is <hi>highly diſpleaſing to God,</hi> and comes under the reprehenſion of the Holy Ghoſt in the laſt of the <hi>Revelation, he that addeth to the words of this book,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore it behoveth you that ſtand ſo much for tythes, to examine well and ſeriouſly your own hearts, and repent of this your evill practice, leſt the ſin you charge upon others be not one day laid to your charge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the laſt refuge you have is this, that it is a ſin will cry for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gcance, when the ſinner on his death-bed is crying for mercy, as appcars by that remarkable Scripture, James.</hi> 5.3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now if the hire of the labourers in mans vineyard kept back by fraud cryeth, how dreadfull will the cry be of the hire of Gods labourers in Gods Vineyard, kept back by robbers and defrauders! I tremble to think of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We hope by the time you have read read over the replies to your former rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Propoſition, your ſpirit will be more calm then here you have ſhew'd your ſelf, but that it is uſuall with many of you to thunder out hell
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64968:19"/>and damnation againſt all thoſe that cannot through conſcicure truly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened obey your humane traditions and legall ceremonies, and forget and leave out <hi>judgement and the love of God,</hi> as if the worſhip of God conſiſted in thoſe aboliſhed legall rites and ceremonies; but in this, you ſeem to ſhew little of the ſpirit of him, that is the <hi>good Shepheard of the Sheep,</hi> but rather like ravening Wolves you ſeek to devoure them; But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, as you have well ſaid to that purpoſe, that you are defrauded of your hire, do you not herein demonſtrate you ſelves to be hirelings? therefore in <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. <hi>The Hireling is no good Shepheard, but comes in as the wrong door, and is a thtefe and a robber;</hi> and how many of theſe hirelings, both in Company and City have for a time cominaed in a Pariſh, but when they have heard of a greater living or parſonage, have relinquished their flock, and given it over to ſtranges, or left it deſtiture. Will not this ſin at that day riſe up in judgement againſt many of you <hi>Tythes-Prieſts?</hi> Ye can be contented to call your ſelves <hi>Goſpel Ministers,</hi> which (if you were) ye would not ſtrive ſo much to ſet up the rites and ceremonies of the Leviticall Law; ye would rather preach Jeſus Chriſt, and that freely from a principle of love; and as long as you continut thus in your outragious cry, and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious judgings, (which are but the paſſions of the mind, which the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God have learned to crucifie with Chriſt) you do but the more make out the truth of the Word, that the ſtrength of your Kingdome is going down, and the fear thereof makes you cry out for help, and uſe all unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full means to make good your argument, even to the wreſting of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, as that in <hi>Luke</hi> 11.42. upon which is built all your whole Fabrick, which appears like all the reſt to be built upon a ſandy foundation, which is falling, and ſhall fall to the ground, and God will put it into the hears of his people, that they ſhall vindicate the truth in this particular. O that the Rulers of this Nation would diſcharge their Vow to Almighty God, in ſetting this Nation at liberty from this great and unſupportable burthen of tythes, which is not only (as hath been proved) Anti-chriſtian, but a bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, even like that of the Aegyptians over the children of Iſael; for as they ſet Taskmaſters over them, ſo theſe Prieſts more like Aegyptians then Chriſtians, do ſet Taskmaſters over the people to enforce them, and that againſt their conſciences to pay: and are there not ſome now in priſon upon the ſame accomptſ and others under proſecution alſo, and will not their cry aſcend up into the ears of the Lord for vengeance? Oh that particular intereſts into unlawfull gain were not that which doth blin the eyes of many of this Nation, that they cannot make uſe of the opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which God hath put into their hands: But it is our hope, that as the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down of Biſhops (who were as <hi>Lords over Gods Heritage</hi>) was one of the firſt of the <hi>Worthtes in Parliament,</hi> ſo the taking away of Tythes ſhall not be the laſt which ſhall be acted by them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
